Guide to the Philip Hart Dunning Papers, 1915-1968 CTC.1976.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Philip Hart Dunning Papers
1915–1968
CTC.1976.01
ULS Archives & Special Collections
3.3 linear feet (8 boxes)
Phillip Hart Dunning was a playwright, producer, director, stage manager, and as a young man also an actor. He is best known as the co-author and co-director, with George Abbott, of the 1926 hit, Broadway. The collection contains play, radio, TV, and film scripts, one novel, and a few short stories. There is a very small amount of related material such as preliminary notes, correspondence, contracts, clippings, etc. included in the collection and filed according to play title with the script.
Dunning, Philip, 1890-1968
Acquisition Information
Gift of George J. Barrere, 1976.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into five series:
I. Philip Dunning as Sole Author
II. Phillip Dunning as Collaborator
III. Phillip Dunning as Adapter
IV. Phillip Dunning as Producer
V. Associated Scripts
Scope and Content Notes
The collection contains many of Philip Hart Dunning’s personal scripts which include play, radio, TV, and film scripts, one novel, and a few short stories. While the collection represents a large portion of his work, it is by no means complete. A small amount of related material such as preliminary notes, correspondence, contracts, clippings, etc. is included in the collection and filed according to play title with the script. In cases where there is no script, a title is represented only by a synopsis. The collection comprises 94 titles in all, including some associated items, at least one of which is dated after Dunning’s death. In a few cases there is more than one version of a given title. Many of the scripts are original typescripts, however, most are copies, and most have annotations.
Related Material
Script for Sequel to a Verdict (1963) can be found in the Curtis Theater Collection, PS3507/U67854.
Biography
Phillip Hart Dunning [December 11, 1892 (One source, The Biographical Encyclopedia and Who’s Who of the American Theatre, 1966, lists 1891 as Dunning’s birth date.) – July 20, 1968], playwright, producer, director, stage manager, and as a young man also an actor, began a long theatrical career in 1910 as assistant manager with a small part in Pomander Walk (Script not included in Dunning collection.). He wrote his first play, Dollar Bill, in 1915. He is best known as the co-author and co-director, with George Abbott, of the 1926 hit, Broadway, and his collaboration as author, producer, or director with Abbott continues into the 1930s, including Lilly Turner (1932), the Hecht-MacArthur play, Twentieth Century (1932), Heat Lightning (1933), The Drums Begin (1933), and Kill That Story (1934) which he wrote with Harry Madden. Without Abbott, Dunning produced Page Miss Glory (1930), written with Joseph Schrank and produced with Lawrence Schwab, Remember the Day (1935), which he wrote and produced with Philo Higley, and his final Broadway production, Schoolhouse on the Lot (1938), which he also directed. Dunning had begun to write screen plays some ten years earlier, and he continues to write for the movies until at least 1948, adapting many of the Broadway plays with which he had been associated to the screen. In the 1950’s and 1960’s he turned his craftsmanship to television. He was also a regular Variety by-liner, and for a short time, 1960-1963, edited the Dramatists Bulletin, organ of the Dramatists Guild. Although a prolific writer, he published only one play, Sequel to a Verdict (1963). When he died in 1968 at age 76, he left a completed play, also with a courtroom setting, A Fantastic Chain of Events, based on the Kennedy assassination. Among his survivors was his brother, Caesar Dunn, also a playwright.
Previous Citation
Philip Hart Dunning Papers, 1915-1968, CTC.1976.01, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Philip Hart Dunning Papers, 1915-1968, CTC.11, Curtis Theatre Collection, Special Collections Department, University of Pittsburgh
Abbott, George, 1887-1995; Andrews, Charlton, 1878-1939; Dramatists Guild.; Dunning, Philip, 1890-1968. Broadway; Dunning, Philip, 1890-1968. Dollar bill.; Dunning, Philip, 1890-1968. Fantastic chain of events; Dunning, Philip, 1890-1968. Little ivory ball; Dunning, Philip, 1890-1968. Sequel to a verdict; Dunning, Philip, 1890-1968; Hecht, Ben, 1893-1964; Higley, Philo; MacArthur, Charles, 1895-1956; Schrank, Joseph; Clippings (Information artifacts); Contracts; Correspondence; Dramatists; Dramatists bulletin; Notes; Performing arts -- Production and direction; Performing arts -- United States; Personal papers; Scripts (Documents); Theater; Theater -- United States; Typescripts; Variety
- Philip Dunning as Sole Author, 1915-1968; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  This series is arranged alphabetically by script title. It includes Dunning’s first play, Dollar Bill, and unpublished novel, Little Ivory Ball (1947), and notes relating to Sequel to a Verdict, also various scripts written under various pseudonyms.
  - Biographical information, 1966-1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Andy McGluke. Written for TV. Plays: Andy McGluke Quits College, Andy McGluke’s Dress Suit, Andy McGluke’s Ringside Seat, Andy McGluke’s Birthday party (Folder 2-3)
  - Andy McGluke. Five of the finest. Plays: The Old Gent’s Footsteps, Almost Promoted, Ringside Arrest, Wild Goose Chase (Folder 4)
  - Away Up Yonder; a new play. Registered under previous title: The Big Attraction. Latest version July 1967. With revisions, 1964 (Folder 5)
  - The Big Depression. As presented at the Lambs Gambol, January 11, 1931. With penciled annotations and corrections, 1930 (Folder 6)
  - The Big Puff; a new comedy. With revisions (Folder 7)
  - Boy and Girl, 1920 (Folder 8)
  - The Colored Actress and the Nigger Porter (water damaged), 1920 (Folder 9)
  - Copacabana; a filmusical synopsis, 1945 (Folder 10)
  - Could I Borrow a Match? A comedy in one act (Folder 11)
  - The Crime of the Century. Screen version. With revisions, 1935 (Folder 12)
    See Also
    3:15.
  - Curtain Going Up; [film] treatment. Revised July 1948 (Folder 13)
  - Curtain Going Up. Miscellaneous notes and clippings (Folder 14)
  - Curtain Going Up. Revised August 1948 (Folder 15)
  - Dollar Bill; or, Spuds. A farcical adventure. Dunning's 1st play, 1915 (Folder 16)
  - Dollars and Horse Sense. Mimeograph. Includes wardrobe, property, light, sound, and motion picture plots (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Dollars and Horse Sense. Without plots (Folder 2)
  - Elmer Tosses a Party (Folder 3)
  - Happy Home (Folder 4)
  - Home and Mother; or, Back to Earth. Alternate title: Never Too Late, 1916 (Folder 5)
  - Horses are Honest; a television play (Folder 6-7)
  - Jury Play. Notes for play idea. Holograph, 1959 (Folder 8)
    3:11-13.
  - Jury Play. Clippings and data, 1959 (Folder 9)
  - King of Coffee; a musical play in two acts. Music by Brazilian composers [not included] (Folder 10)
  - Knee Deep in Diamonds; a television play (Folder 11)
  - The Last Rehearsal (Folder 12)
  - Let There be Light; a new play. Mimeograph copy (Folder 13)
  - Little Brown Jug (Folder 14)
  - Little Ivory Ball, a novel. Includes TLS rejection from Satevepost, 1947, and news clips (Folder 15)
  - Little Man in a High Hat; a screen play. With penciled notes (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
  - Little Tin Badge. By William Miller and Ben Madden [pseudonyms for P. Dunning] (Folder 3)
  - Money Don’t Grow on Trees; a comedy in one act. With inked revisions (Folder 4)
  - The Mysterious Mystery. With penciled notes (Folder 5)
  - Night Hostess; scenario (Folder 6)
  - One Born Every Minute (Folder 7)
  - Pardon My Gun; blood and thunder with music. Book by D.V. Hart. [Pseud. for P. Dunning.] With penciled notes (Folder 8)
  - The Professional, 1930 (Folder 9)
  - Run for Your Money; a television play (Folder 10)
  - Sequel to a Verdict. Notes, outline, plots, ground plan, etc. (Play published by Dramatists Play Service, 1963. Previously referred to a Courtroom Play; original title: Account of a Trial) (Folder 11)
    2:8-9
  - Sequel to a Verdict. Background clippings and data (Folder 12)
  - Sequel to a Verdict. Correspondence, 1959-1962 (Folder 13)
  - Sh! Sh! Listen! Alternate title on cover: Ether Waves (Folder 14)
  - Shadow of Doubt; or, The Crime of the Century (Folder 15)
    1:12.
  - Show Folks (Folder 16)
  - Show Beautiful Snow. Version 1, 11p. With inked revisions (Folder 17)
  - Show Beautiful Snow. Version 2, 20p (Folder 18)
  - Spontaneous Combustion: a new play by David Hart and Mary Niles Van Loon [Pseuds. for P. Dunning] (Folder 19)
  - Sweet Land of Liberty. A new play in two acts (Folder 20)
  - Sweet Land of Liberty. A new play in three acts, 1929 (Folder 21)
  - The 13th Year of Abie and His Irish Rose; a satirical burlesque (Folder 22)
  - This is My girl; screenplay treatment (Folder 23)
  - Too True; or, Sock ‘em on the Bean. With inked revisions (Folder 24)
  - Two Dollar Bettor. [Short story] Alternate title inked on cover: Two Horse Parlay (Folder 25)
- Philip Dunning as Collaborator, 1927-1971; II.
  Series II is arranged alphabetically by the name of the co-author. It includes the final script, the tryout version, a television adaptation, and two later play adaptations by George Abbott, of the play Broadway. Among the other collaborators are Charlton Andrews, Philo Higley ( Remember the Day (1935) includes stage inventories, reviews, etc.), John Mcnulty, Harry Madden, and others.
  - With George Abbott. The Big Shot. Book by George Abbot. Based on Broadway (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - With George Abbott. Broadway; a play in three acts. Tryout version (Folder 2)
  - With George Abbott. Broadway; a play in three acts. Adapted for television as a drama with music by P. Dunning (Folder 3)
  - With George Abbott. A Party at the Paradise; a two act play by George Abbott, based on Broadway (Folder 4)
  - With George Abbott. Speak Easy. Book by George Abbott. Inked on t.p., 1971 (Folder 5)
  - With Charlton Andrews. Hoky Hollywood; a farce in three acts. With revisions, 1927 (Folder 6)
  - With John Beane. Head over Heart; a new comedy (Folder 7)
  - With Curtis Benton. The late John Barleycorn; a Travesty on Prohibition. Telephone business by P. Dunning (Folder 8)
  - With Hal Borland. America is Americans; a Patriotic Playlet. On cover: Corrected. Mimeograph copy (Folder 9)
  - With Barton Browne. Royal Strings, 1936 (Folder 10)
  - With Jack Donahue. The Understudy; a comedy in three acts (Folder 11)
  - With Jo Eisinger and Stephen Van Gluck. Public Benefactor; an original melodrama in three acts. Collaboration agreement with Philip Dunning and optioned by Dunning. Motion picture on theme made by MGM (stained), 1936 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - With Rita Q. Ford. Three Girls and a Pearl; a new comedy, 1940 (Folder 2)
  - With Milton Gropper. Anything for a Laugh, 1941 (Folder 3)
  - With Lawrence Gross. Face Values; a new comedy in two acts, 1935 (Folder 4)
  - With James Hagan. Double in Brass; screen play scenario (Folder 5)
  - With Sam Hellman and Abel Green. Notes and suggestions by P. Dunning on Mr. Broadway, screen play by Hellman and Green (Folder 6)
  - With Philo Higley. Remember the Day; a new play. Mimeograph copy, 1935 (Folder 7)
  - With Philo Higley. Remember the Day; a new play. Reviewed 1963. Includes theatre flyer, 1935 (Folder 8)
  - With Philo Higley. Remember the Day; a new play. Stage manager’s inventories; wardrobe, electrical materials, properties, scenery (Folder 9)
  - With Philo Higley. Remember the Day; a new play. Reviews of the production at the National Theatre, September, 1935 (Folder 10)
  - With Philo Higley. Remember the Day; a new play. Screen treatment for new ending, by P. Dunning (Folder 11)
  - With N.C. Hunter. Palm Beach; a comedy in three acts (Folder 12)
  - With John McNulty. What Goes on Here. Based on John McNulty’s New Yorker stories. April draft, 1943 (Folder 13)
  - With John McNulty. What Goes on Here. With penciled notes. September, 1944 (Folder 14)
  - With John McNulty. What Goes on Here. Stage diagrams (Folder 15)
  - With John McNulty. What Goes on Here. Dunning’s “Notes and rough layout” for McNulty’s stories. February, 1943 (Folder 16)
  - With John McNulty. What Goes on Here. Paramount contracts (movie title: Third Avenue), signed and notarized carbon; TLS from Paramount, 1945 (Folder 17)
  - With John McNulty. What Goes on Here. 11 New Yorker stories. Clippings, 1941-1942 (Folder 18)
  - With Harry Madden. Bedtime for Ali Baba; a play in two acts and seven scenes. Mimeograph copy, 1936 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - With Harry Madden. Kill That Story. MGM synopsis. Summer tryout, Langner’s Country Theatre, Westport. Mimeograph copy, 1934 (Folder 2)
  - With Joseph Schrank. Page Miss Glory; 2 plays in two acts. Mimeograph copy, 1934 (Folder 3)
  - With Charles Sherman. A Thousand Times, no. 1939. Mimeograph copy (Folder 4-5)
  - With Robert Wilder. A new play by P. Dunning and Robert Wilder. Dunning’s 1st draft of Act I, from Wilder’s novel, Flamingo Road (Folder 6)
  - With Louis Wolheim. History Repeats Itself; or, Even in Robe. Talking picture scenario. 1st draft, 1930 (Folder 7)
- Philip Dunning as Adaptor, 1936-1944; III.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by the original author of the play.
  - Farrago, Alexander. Playland (working title). A play in three acts. Translated from Hungarian. P. Dunning’s version, 1936 (Folder 8)
  - Hagan, James, and P. Dunning. Reaching for a Star [short story] by P. Dunning based on a play by Hagan and Dunning (Folder 9)
  - Mack, Willard. The Dove. Dialogue adaptation by James Ashmore Creelman. Screen version of Broadway play [adapted by P. Dunning?] Mimeograph copy with penciled notes (Folder 10)
  - Wector, Dixon. Johnny Comes Marching Home. Synopses of adaptations by P. Dunning. With notes (Folder 11)
  - Wector, Dixon. Johnny Comes Marching Home. Armstrong’s Theatre of Today script. November 11. Mimeograph copy, 1944 (Folder 12)
  - Wector, Dixon. Johnny Comes Marching Home. P. Dunning’s notes. Holograph (Folder 13)
- Philip Dunning as Producer, 1932-1945; IV.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by author of the play. Includes the script, photographs, and stage inventories for the play Schoolhouse on the Lot which had its Broadway premiere at the Ritz Theatre on March 22, 1938.
  Dunning was also the producer for the following productions - Broadway, Night Hostess, Sweet Land of Liberty, Kill that Story, Page Miss Glory, Remember the Day. The materials for these shows appear in the earlier series.
  - Fields, Joseph A. and Jerome Comoro. Schoolhouse on the Lot; a play, 1938 (Box 7, Folders 1-2)
  - Fields, Joseph A. and Jerome Comoro. Schoolhouse on the Lot; a play. Photographs (Folder 3)
  - Fields, Joseph A. and Jerome Comoro. Schoolhouse on the Lot; a play. Miscellany: 3TLS, flyers; clippings, 1938 (Folder 4)
  - Ford, Rita Q. Some Like It Hot. Contract for try-out at Pine Grove Playhouse, Cambridge Springs, Pennsylvania, 1941 (Folder 5)
  - Hecht, Ben and Charles MacArthur. Twentieth Century. a new play based on a play by Charles Millholland. Property of Abbot-Dunning, Inc. Mimeograph copy with penciled notes. Includes ground plans and program, 1932 (Folder 6)
  - Klee, Lawrence. The Sergeant. Victory players script. American Theatre Wing. Produced in Connecticut by P. Dunning. Mimeograph copy, 1945 (Folder 7)
- Associated Materials, 1943-1959; V.
  This series collects the scripts of Dunning's brother, playwright and screen writer Caesar Dunn. All of the scripts in this series are undated. There is also one folder of newspaper clippings relating to Philip Dunning.
  - The Bridal Sweetie (Folder 8-9)
  - The Bridal Sweetie. Broadway Bandits; a tonsorial satire (Folder 10)
  - Caresses; a continental comedy of the art studios (Folder 11-12)
  - The Count; a play (Folder 13)
  - A Gay Deceiver. Transcript (Folder 14)
  - Jury Duty for Maggie; a musical dream (Folder 15)
  - The Love Doctor. 2 copies. Includes published columns (clippings) (Folder 16)
  - Moral Man; a financial farce (Folder 17)
  - Only a Husband (Folder 18-19)
  - Silhouette (Box 8, Folder 1-2)
  - The State Trooper (Folder 3-4)
  - What the Doctor Ordered; a laughing prescription. Mimeograph (Folder 5)
  - Women at Races. 2 copies. Includes published column (clipping) (Folder 6)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1943-1959 (Folder 7)